"The Side Effects
of Burning Incense"
Frankincense and myrrh date
back to thousands of years
before the three wise men.
The burning of witch's incense
may have actually had
a hygienic functions,
like maybe repelling mosquitoes,
and when put to the test,
incense fumes were able to kill off
some bacteria and mold in the air
but may also carry health risks.
Although the adverse health effects
of second-hand tobacco smoke
are well recognized, the impact
of burning incense in the home
has received less attention, but
burning incense has been found
to generate like four times the
particulate matter as cigarettes;
so, incense may be even worse!
No wonder home incense use
may have significant adverse
health effects, particularly
on the heart and lungs,
including childhood asthma.
No wonder, since the incense
smoke particle size
peaks down in the danger range,
so ultrafine they can float
down into the deepest
parts of the lungs.
It’s not just the little ash
particles in the smoke though,
there’s carbon monoxide, nitric
oxides, sulfur dioxide,
carcinogenic polycyclic
aromatic hydrocarbons,
and volatile organic compounds
like benzene and formaldehyde.
The World Health Organization suggests
limiting indoor formaldehyde
to about 80 parts per billion,
but even with a window open
during the hour or so
incense is burning,
formaldehyde levels
exceed the safety limit.
What does this all mean in
terms of disease outcomes?
Studies on rats show incense can
do all sorts of terrible things,
but what about people?
A study of thousands of children
followed over time found
that exposure to household
incense burning was associated
with impaired lung function,
reduced lung function growth,
and increased risks of
respiratory diseases and symptoms.
Daily exposure is associated
with impaired lung function
in adolescents too, though
interestingly those who had
pets at home appeared to
have better lung function.
Something I noted previously, how
having a dog or cat in the house
during early life may protect against
childhood asthma and allergy.
What about the heart?
Long-term exposure to incense
burning in the home environment
was associated with an increased
risk of cardiovascular mortality.
Approximately 8 percent of
heart disease deaths and
12 percent of stroke deaths could
potentially be attributed
to incense use, though they were
looking at long-term exposure,
so like incense burning at home on
a daily basis for more than 20 years.
What about cancer?
Temple workers exposed to incense
day in and day out were found
to have evidence of
signiﬁcantly more DNA damage,
including DNA strand breaks.
Does this translate
into greater cancer risk?
One unsolved mystery has been
why non-smoking Asian women
have such high lung cancer rates.
Might it be incense?
Probably not, since the
association between incense use
and lung cancer
remains inconclusive,
though incense use does
appear to be linked to cancers
of the upper respiratory tract,
as well as brain tumors
among children whose mother
were exposed to incense.
Three times the odds, even more
than that of second-hand smoke.
In fact, even more than the
consumption of bologna sandwiches.
Processed meat consumption
only appears to at most
double brain tumor
risk among children.
Even without tumors, a study of
15,000 infants found that
household incense burning
was associated with a delay
in brain development milestones
such as when they start to walk.
And then on the other
side of the life cycle,
incense exposure among older adults
was associated with reduced
cognitive performance and adverse
structural changes in the brain.
The researchers conclude that
this calls for safer practices,
such as avoiding
burning incense indoors
or using safer incense alternatives.
So-called environmentally friendly
types of incense have been
put to the test, and…
they were found to contain
even higher concentrations
of several potentially carcinogenic
polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons.
Despite being a
recognized health hazard,
burning incense remains
in widespread use.
In the very least, we may want to
avoid burning incense in the home
when susceptible
individuals are present,
such as the very young,
the very old, or
people with a family history of
allergy or pre-existing
cardiovascular or respiratory disease.
One innovative suggestion
is electronic incense,
like the e-cigarette
of the incense world,
so you can get the fragrance
without the combustion
by-products of smoke.
Most of the concern about
e-cigarette-related adverse events
traditionally have revolved
around the nicotine,
which wouldn’t be a
problem with e-incense,
the concern that e-cigarette use
would lead to real cigarette use.
But now that there have been
thousands of cases of lung injury
associated with vaping, and
we’re still actually not sure
what’s causing the issue,
it seems to me we
should figure that out
before we push for the
electronic incense equivalent.
One option in the meantime
is scented candles,
which, under normal
conditions of use,
do not appear to pose known
health risks to the consumer.